Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Natalia Kanem FA1722
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Office Files of Natalia Kanem
2000-2004
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kanem, Natalia
Ford Foundation
FA1722
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 Hollinger boxes
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Briefing books, reports, and publications, 2000-2004
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:182.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office Files Natalia Kanem created and organized when she served as Deputy Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ). It consists of one series of briefing books, reports, and various kinds of publications. The briefing books document Kanem's participation at different PSJ and larger Foundation meetings she attended between 2000 and 2004. Materials within the collection chiefly concern the state and development of civil society and peace and international cooperation throughout the world as well as the Foundation's support of research and programs focusing on those areas.
Biographical / Historical
Natalia Kanem is a medical doctor who has worked in the fields of public health, reproductive health and sexuality, peace and international cooperation, and human rights and social justice. Her career encompasses positions in academia, philanthropy, and the United Nations. She held various posts at the Ford Foundation between 1992 and 2005 and is the current Executive Director of the United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA).
While at the Ford Foundation, Kanem's position changed from Program Officer for Women's Reproductive Health and Sexuality at the Lagos, Nigeria Office, to Representative for West Africa, to Senior Director of Management Services, to her final position as Deputy Vice President of the Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ).
Kanem received a BA in history and science from Harvard University, an MD from Columbia University, and a Master's degree in public health with specializations in epidemiology and preventative medicine from the University of Washington. She joined the UNFPA in 2014 as the Country Representative for Tanzania, and then in 2016, she became Deputy Executive Director in charge of Programmes. She was appointed UNFPA Executive Director in 2017.
Ford Foundation; Civil society; International relations; Peace
- Briefing books, reports, and publications, 2000-2004; 1; .76 Cubic Feet About 2 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the briefing books, reports, and various publications collected by Natalia Kanem between 2000 and 2004. Kanem served as Deputy Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) during this time, and the materials within the series chiefly concern the state and development of civil society and peace and international cooperation throughout the world as well as the Foundation's support of research and programs focusing on those areas. Kanem accumulated the briefing books in the series through her participation in different PSJ and larger Foundation meetings. The assortment of publications within the series include a directory and a book on civil society by Michael Edwards, Director of the Ford Foundation's Governance and Civil Society Unit (GCS).
  - Civil Society - Michael Edwards, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Philanthropy Learning Group (PLG) meeting, Pocantico, New York, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Strategic Assessment: The Ford Foundation's Corporate Involvement (CI) Initiative, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - State and Society: Building Alliances for Social Change - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Spring Trip to China, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Towards Enhanced Work on Conflict: A Consultancy for the Ford Foundation, 2001 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Joint Worldwide Meeting - Working Locally/Working Globally: Advancing Equity, Justice, and Pluralism in the 21st Century, San Francisco, California, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation staff photograph album mock-up, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Indian Research and Grants Assessment Project Draft Report, 2001 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Think Tanks and Research Centers Funded by the Human Rights Unit, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting, Krakow, Poland, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Governance and Civil Society (GCS) meeting, Pocantico, New York, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)